This readme file and the data files are prepared by Mehmet Talha Cakmak and Süleyman Acar.

This is a gold standard test data which consists of 300 manually aligned English-Turkish sentences.
The data is collected from old language proficiency exams organized by ÖSYM (Student Selection and Placement Center of Turkey). These exams include questions which consist of high quality exact translations for English-Turkish. The data is aligned manually.

Please cite the following reference while using the related data.

Mehmet Talha Cakmak , Süleyman Acar , Gülşen Eryiğit. Word alignment for English-Turkish language pair. In Proceedings of the Eighth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation, LREC 2012, Istanbul, May 2012.

@InProceedings{cakmakmeh2012,
author = {Mehmet Talha Cakmak and S{\"u}leyman Acar and G{\"u}l{\c s}en Eryi{\u g}it},
title = {Word Alignment for English-Turkish Language Pair},
booktitle = {Proceedings of the Eighth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC)},
month = {23-25 May}, year = {2012}, address = {Istanbul, Turkey}
} 


English.txt
It contains 300 English sentences. Each row contains one sentence.

Turkish.txt
It contains 300 Turkish sentences. Each row contains one sentence.

aligment.txt
It contains 300 alignment. Each row contains one alignment of Turkish-English sentence pair.
Each aligment is seperated by semicolon in one whole alignment. Each number corresponds to 
words in English or Turkish sentence. First numbers corresponds to English words. Others
corresponds to Turkish words. 0 corresponds NULL.

For example:
English sentence: I was not able to finish my homework .
Turkish sentence: Ödevimi bitiremedim .
alignment: 0 0 ; 1 2 ; 2 2 ; 3 2 ; 4 2 ; 5 0 ; 6 2 ; 7 1 ; 8 1 ; 9 3 ;

0 0 ; --> NULL-NULL (There is no non-Turkish words for a English word in this sentence pair.)  
1 2 ; --> I-bitiremedim
2 2 ; --> was-bitiremedim
3 2 ; --> not-bitiremedim
4 2 ; --> able-bitiremedim
5 0 ; --> to-NULL (There is no any Turkish word for "to" in this sentence pair.)
6 2 ; --> finish-bitiremedim
7 1 ; --> my-ödevimi
8 1 ; --> homework-ödevimi
9 3 ; --> .-.

